Much has been said about the era of the
like one person one billion dollar
company. And honestly, I think we're not
too far from it. We've seen and invested
in companies that are doing a million
plus in ARR per employee, which is just
like kind of a crazy metric that we
haven't seen before. We're also just so
early. I don't think we've yet seen what
the cloud code for marketers and product
people and sales people and all of that
looks like. And so, I actually think
things are just going to continue to get
more efficient from here and it's going
to free up humans to spend their time on
the things that humans can uniquely do
like generating ideas and spending time
with customers and all of that.
>> Hello, I'm your host David Barnard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
Cat's State of Subscription Apps Report.
Each episode in this series will explore
one crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Olivia Moore,
AI partner at Andreessen Horowitz. On
the podcast, I talked with Olivia about
the tailwinds driving a boom in non-game
app revenue, how vibe coding and AI
workflows are fueling growth in
categories that have nothing to do with
AI, and why people predicting the death
of apps have never been more wrong. Hey
Olivia, thanks so much for joining me on
the podcast today.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> Super excited to have you of all people
to talk about the state of subscription
app economy and the app economy
generally. You know, you've been
covering consumer for a while now at
Andreessen Horowitz and constantly
sharing great content on Twitter, on
Andreessen Horowitz blog, and been on
podcasts and other stuff like that. Um
so, I thought you'd be the perfect
person to get on to kind of talk about
what's going on with apps in 2026 and
there's just a lot going on. So, why
don't we start at the at the highest of
high levels? You know, revenue was up
last year, that's a good thing, right?
>> Yeah. It's very exciting. I feel like
I've been a consumer investor for a
decade and now has been the most fun
time to invest in consumer apps because
so many things are actually working. I
think the big stat that a lot of people
are are rightfully excited about is the
fact that consumer application in-app
purchases finally passed games. And like
a decade ago it was like six to one the
other way. So it's been a really big and
meaningful shift which is very exciting
to see. Um and AI has been like a big
big component of that which is not
surprising.
>> Yeah, one of the exciting things that I
saw as well is that I would have guessed
a larger percentage of the increase, the
21% year-over-year growth in non-game
apps, which again amounts to like
billions and billions of dollars. And so
only 3 and 1/2 billion of that according
to Sensor Tower was attributed to
generative AI.
There was billions of increased revenue
across movie and TV shows, billions in
social media, billions in utilities. So
it seemed like it was a pretty
wide-ranging
increase in revenue. It wasn't just
concentrated in AI apps.
>> Absolutely, yeah. And I think that
reflects the fact that like you know,
there's been a lot of discussion of vibe
coding, but it's very true that like
building and marketing a product is just
getting a lot more efficient. And you're
also able to bake in more features to
products that using AI that make
consumers more willing to pay for them.
Maybe another example of a category
that's not technically AI that saw a ton
of growth is short dramas. Um both in
downloads and in revenue, they're
making, you know, hundreds of millions
of dollars now. And I personally have
met several startups that are largely
using AI to either fully generate or
edit these short dramas. And so then
they can make them at much lower cost
and spend more on marketing to
distribute them and and it's a very
fascinating dynamic.
>> Yeah, the integration of AI and AI
workflows into existing apps is a
fascinating aspect of this boom. But I
mean AI-generative apps did make up a
large share of that revenue. What do you
think about that? And and how does that
look going forward?
>> I think they both made up a big and
increasing share. I think AI in-app
purchases were up something like 3x
year-over-year, which is is the most
notable, I think, of all the main
categories. Like, and yet, I think it's
still so early. Like, if you look at top
10 apps by saturation of every age
group, like, you know, 18 to 25, 35 to
40, ChatGPT is the only AI app that
cracks the top 10 for any age groups,
which is crazy. And so, I think we're
just very early in like the types of AI
apps that are popping up on mobile in
particular. All of the top ones are like
ChatGPT, Claude, DALL-E, like these very
general LLM assistants. And I think as
it's become easier to productize the
models and also just serve the models on
mobile, we're going to see like a a big
and exciting expansion in the types of
AI products that that are being
delivered via phone.
>> Yeah, and that's such a great point. And
and I'll just list them off because I
did find this really fascinating is that
as you said, you know, it feels like
it's been the year of AI. That's what
everybody's talking about. ChatGPT
obviously had a banner year. But, you go
through and the top apps are YouTube,
Instagram, Spotify, Amazon, Facebook,
WhatsApp, Discord, which I think is new
in the chart this year, Messenger, and
then ChatGPT.
Um and that's for male. And for female,
ChatGPT doesn't even make the top 10.
So, we are seeing a you know, people
have been predicting the death of apps
for
more than a decade now, but 2026 was a
banner year, and it wasn't just AI
driving it, which I think is especially
fascinating.
>> Totally. And I think it's a testament to
how big and how mainstream so many of
these other apps are that even if
ChatGPT is on the top of the App Store
every single day and got the most
downloads last year, like, it's a it's a
big hurdle to climb to start to replace
Google or something like that, but feels
like we're seeing the glimmers of that
starting to happen.
>> I wanted to talk next about what you see
as the tailwinds of this AI boom. And
one of the things that that I
specifically wanted to discuss is that
it feels like, and maybe you'll have
some more anecdota or some data to back
it up, but it feels like people paying
20 bucks a month for ChatGPT and getting
a lot of value out of it, has kind of
opened the pocketbooks a little that
people are more willing to spend. What
What do you think on that front?
>> It's absolutely something that we're
seeing. So, I mentioned I've been a
consumer investor for a while. Anytime
building a marketplace, like the
idea that you would want to or be able
to monetize your users in the first five
or 10 years was pretty crazy. Like, the
users were the product. You would make
money by serving them ads. There were
some examples of great subscription
companies like Acombra or Duolingo, but
to be honest, they were kind of few and
far between pre-AI. Like, consumers were
just not willing to pay directly for
products. We've seen that completely
change. And to your point, it's not just
the $60 a year anymore, which feels like
it was kind of the preset pre-AI
consumer subscription. I think ChatGPT
anchored a lot of people on $20 a month,
if not more. And when you incorporate
usage-based pricing, you can have whales
on consumer apps that are paying, you
know, hundreds of dollars, if not
thousands of dollars a month, which is
something we've never seen before.
>> Yeah, it seems like more and more apps
are experimenting with higher tiers,
with hybrid monetization. And then even
ChatGPT itself just introduced ads. So,
this, you know, hybrid monetization is a
big part of this growth as well. Is that
you are seeing more consumers willing to
pay, but we're finding better ways to
monetize those users who are willing to
pay, better meet the demand curve. And,
you know, back to good old ads to
monetize those who aren't willing to
pay. So, it does seem like there the
revenue potential is pretty broad-based
and it's not just subscriptions. It's
not just ads. It's it's a a pretty
healthy mix.
>> Yes, this is a topic I'm fascinated by,
which is that as an econ major, we are
getting closer to being able to
perfectly price segment users and like
hypothetically narrow consumer surplus
and increase the value that these
products could capture. Ads versus
subscriptions is one example. I tweeted
the other week about like Grinder now
has like a several hundred dollars a
month for an AI that like swipes and
makes matches for you. Is the average
user going to pay for that? No, not at
all, but like 1% of users will and
you're now able as an app to capture
like so much more value from what you
provide than than what was possible
pre-AI cuz you're essentially serving
not just the product anymore, but you
can serve outcomes if people are willing
to pay for them.
>> Right. And and specifically on price and
you kind of already touched on it, but
anything else to dive into related to
just the increase average revenue per
user, the increase in spending.
>> We actually pulled
data kind of on the top, you know, 50
100 AI applications. We publish a list
of these every 6 months and and what we
found is that these companies are
monetizing at two times the average
revenue per user if not higher than like
the pre-AI complements. And they're, you
know, the fact that they're monetizing
at all so early is is exciting. We
looked at kind of proprietary data
across the first, you know, 18 20 months
of gen AI pitches. And consumer
businesses are ramping revenue faster
than enterprise businesses, which I
think has never before been true in
probably the history of software and I
think reflects kind of the the size of
the opportunity now.
>> As an investor, how are you looking at
this? You know, obviously for something
to be venture investable, it needs to
have the potential to be a multi-billion
dollar outcome. Or does it? I mean, you
can correct me if if you're thinking
about it differently, but then how do
you think about the investability of
these consumer apps? You cuz we are
seeing apps get to 10 million super
quick, 20 million super quick, but are
they going to go from 20 million to 200
million to 600 million to be these like
next Duolingo's or Life360 or these
other big publicly traded subscription
apps?
>> This is something we think a lot about,
and I think there's a couple layers to
it. One would be this concept of what I
call like giving away dollars for a
pennies, which would be that a lot of
startups now are achieving really fast
growth by essentially subsidizing the
model costs to the end consumer. So,
like giving away nano banana pro nano
banana pro for free, things like that.
And you can get very fast growth that
way. To me, it's almost similar to like
the on-demand economy, like Uber,
DoorDash, a trillion other apps. Most of
those, the unit economics catch up to
you eventually. In some cases, you're
able to achieve like escape velocity
almost, and then make make users
profitable, but I think you have to be
quite quite good at like marketing and
distribution and really lock users into
the product if you're going to grow that
way. The other element that we think
about a lot is what the big labs and
model companies are doing and what the
incumbents are doing and like how does
that impact you as a standalone consumer
product? We're seeing Claude go
extremely hard on prosumer, ChatGPT
launching their own health product,
trying to own, you know, more of their
own app store. Gemini is doing all the
personal intelligence stuff, and so we
think a lot about where those companies
have the right to win versus where an
independent startup can build something
much more opinionated and almost
verticalized and kind of retain and and
monetize users that way.
>> Yeah, what do you what do you think
about durability of use cases? I mean,
it It feel like we've we've a lot of
consumer apps kind of launch, get a lot
of attention, you know, maybe Be Real
would be a good example. You know, they
really blew up. They seemed like it was
going to be the next, you know, Snapchat
or Facebook or whatever, and then that
the kind of novelty of that wore off.
So, how do you think about looking for
those more durable use cases?
>> Uh Sam Altman actually said something
interesting on the the OpenAI town hall
a couple weeks ago, which is someone
asked him like, are you going to kill my
startup? And he was basically like,
look, like if you as a company are happy
when the models improve, like you're
safe and that's like a great place to
be. And I think that's a function of
we're looking for products that are not
just like thin features that that can
capture like transitory opportunities
because if it's if that's the case and
if it's an obviously good idea, everyone
is going to do it and like you're going
to get price competed down. It's going
to be hard to acquire users. So, I think
to that point, we're looking for teams
that are extremely, I used this word
before, but like opinionated about a
specific use case and will build out and
productize the models in a way that it's
much more compelling, easy to use, more
effective than what like a broad-based
LLM platform will do. I think one
example, like we invested in Gamma,
which does AI for presentations and
slide decks. Like, yes, you can do decks
within ChatGPT, Claude, other products
now, but they're never going to be a
first-class citizen in the way they are
for Gamma and there's kind of like a
real opportunity to to retain users in
that way.
>> Yeah. I also think there are lots of
opportunities in
solving existing use cases with the
fresh perspective of where we're at with
technology in 2026. What's a from the
ground up rethink of what a personal
trainer could be as a fitness app
instead of bolting an AI experience onto
an existing fitness app. You know, I
think there are also opportunities there
for those existing very durable use
cases that apps that have been, you
know, popular. What's a mental health
coach app in this era that Calm was to
the last era? And I don't know that
Calm's going to be the one to crack that
with their kind of legacy app and kind
of having to support those existing use
cases, but maybe the next big kind of
mental health app will be that kind of
fresh perspective with AI at the
foundation of it.
>> Yeah, I totally agree. I think mental
health is a great example because there
are many consumer services like, you
know, therapy, coaching, language
learning, fitness training where
previously like the price point and the
level of access was inaccessible for
most people. And the first version of AI
takes we saw on that were very like
skeuomorphic to the pre-AI service. So,
it was like therapy session, but it cost
$10 because it's run by a voice agent
for 60 minutes. And I think in fact what
we're learning is like yes, a lot of
people don't do therapy because of cost
or access, but for a lot of them the
60-minute session format is it doesn't
work or is not compelling or doesn't fit
into their life. And so, AI is now like
allowing you to reimagine how to build a
different experience or how to let the
consumer build their own experience
actually to like deliver products that
they they haven't found compelling
enough to to use or pay for before.
>> Yeah, that's a great point. The last
thing I want to touch on was AI as an
accelerant for everything.
I mean, from product development to
marketing to product discovery, it does
feel like smaller teams can move faster
and then existing teams that have proven
out some level of product market fit can
double down on that and just move
faster. What are you seeing there?
>> Yeah, that's exactly the case. I mean,
we're investors in Cursor and like
seeing the usage on that product grow
and talking to engineers and
um seeing kind of how their day changes
now, even like, you know, product
people, marketing people are scoping
things out on lovable and getting like a
a spec or a new idea approved in like a
day where previously they would have to
loop in a bunch of engineers and it
would take weeks. So, I think like much
has been said about the era of the like
one person, one billion dollar company.
And honestly, I think we're not too far
from it. We've seen and invested in
companies that are doing a million plus
in ARR per employee, which is just like
kind of a crazy metric that we haven't
seen before. Um, and again, like we're
also just so early. Like Claude code has
come to developers, but like we I don't
think we've yet seen what the Claude
code for marketers and product people
and sales people and and all of that
looks like. And so, I actually think
things are just going to continue to get
more efficient from here and it's going
to free up humans to
spend their time on the things that
humans can uniquely do, like generating
ideas and spending time with customers
and all of that.
>> It's going to be wild to see what the
next I mean, even like the next six
months, but much less the next year and
next five years. And then you're you're
in a position where you're having to
make bets that will hopefully pay off in
five to 10 years.
Um, so it's it's fascinating to hear
your perspective, kind of living in the
future and thinking about these things.
Thanks so much for joining me. Anything
you want to share as we wrap up?
Anything our audience can do for you?
>> I would say for me, like, you know, this
is kind of my job, so I have an unfair
advantage, but like the best thing that
you can do to build intuition on these
products is just to use them. Um, and I
think the quality of consumer AI apps on
on mobile is just so much better and
more sophisticated than they were six
months ago. Maybe to like name a few for
people to try if they're interested that
I think are doing compelling things.
We're investors in Wabi, which allows
you to spin up your own mini apps, which
is very cool, and use those created by
others. Um, there's also apps like Gizmo
and Sakai where you can build little
games on a TikTok-like feed, which is
very cool. And then I think we're also
seeing and will see what happens when
you can text AI now, not within an app.
So, products like Poke and Tasklet that
do that. So, yeah, I think the best way
to to stay on top of what's going on is
just to to use the products cuz things
are changing so fast.
>> Can folks pitch you or Andreessen
Horowitz? How does How does that work?
How How should people get in touch if
they think they are building the next
big consumer app?
>> I'm at um Omore Tweets on Twitter. I'm
fairly I'm on there all day, so
hopefully I'm pretty reachable and would
love to hear from anyone building a
consumer AI product.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
joining me. This is a lot of fun.
>> Thank you.
>> [music]
>> Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.